## MD **ASHIQ**UR **RAHMAN**

GRADUATE STUDENT ~ THE UNIVERSITY OF ARIZONA



Tempe, Arizona



+1 (480) 310-7674

marahman@email.arizona.edu



in ashigopu117



ashiqopu



ashigrahman.com

## Skills

Research Computer Networks, Named Data Networking, routing in mobile ad-hoc networks, scheduling

algorithms with network coding in RSU-based vehicular ad-hoc networks (V2I).

C/C++, familiar with Scala, Java and Python; ViM, GDB, Lucene, Docker, NS-3, CSIM. Coding and Tools

> Natural language processing, Database systems, Information retrieval. Others

## **Education**

Graduate (PhD): Computer Science, The University of Arizona, AZ (GPA: 3.75/4.00)

2016-05/2021

- Student Developer: NDN Forwarding Daemon (NFD): (https://named-data.net/doc/NFD/current/). A network forward that evolves together with the NDN architecture.
- NLP: Built a weighted dropout probability-based system to support multi-level token annotation in medical literature. Near SoTA performance with significantly lower training time. Tools: Python, Docker.
- Information Retrieval: Built a (part of) Watson to index and retrieve top relevant Wikipedia pages for short queries similar to the Jeopardy game. Built a spam classifier. Tools: Scala, Lucene.
- DBMS: Implemented heap-file, buffer manager and B+ tree of a MINIBASE database system. Tool: C.
- Networks: Implemented a software router with ARP and PWOSPF protocol supporting link failure. Tool: C.
- Hackathon: 2<sup>nd</sup> Runner-up in 8<sup>th</sup> and Winner in 6<sup>th</sup> and 4th NDN Hackathon.

Relevant Coursework: Principles of Computer Networks; Operating Systems; Database Systems and Implementation; Algorithms in NLP; Text Retrieval & Web Search; Algorithms in Bioinformatics; Computer Graphics; Computer Security.

 Undergraduate (BSc): Computer Science and Engineering, Khulna University of Engineering & Technology (KUET), Bangladesh (GPA: 3.60/4.00)

2011-2015

- Thesis: Application of network coding in scheduling algorithms in multi-RSU vehicular ad-hoc networks. Published six papers from related studies, two as the first author, two as second and two as third. Tool: CSIM.
- Software Development: Implemented a gas station automation software, Tools: C#, .NET, Crystal Reports.
- Programming: Four ACM ICPC regionals, IUT-ICT Fest (best-14th). Workshop manager and trainer.
- Hackathon: Winner, Water Hackathon by World Bank.

• Hardware Project: Designed a car with programmable microcontroller; Logisim and FPGA circuit design.

Relevant Coursework: Software Engineering; Computer Networks; Data Comm.; Machine Learning; Artificial Intelligence; Fault-tolerant systems; Data Structures and Algorithms; Mathematical Analysis; Computer Architecture and Organization; Digital System Design; Microprocessors and Assembly Language; Digital Logic Design; Peripherals and Interfacing.

## **Experience**

Graduate Associate

Computer Science, The University of Arizona, AZ

Research: Architectural differences between Named Data Networking (NDN) and IP in mobile ad-hoc networks (submitted). Routing in challenging networks.

2016-Present

Teaching: CSC 425: Computer Networks (grader and project maintainer), Spring-17, Fall-17, Spring-20. CSC 452: Operating Systems (grader), Fall-19.

Instructor

Computer Science and Engineering, Daffodil International University, Bangladesh

2015-2016

Teaching (in-person): CS 113: Intro to Programming, CS 134 Data Structures, CS 221: Algorithms.

Mentor, Contest organizer and Judge: Competitive programming: Beginner and Intermediate.

Workshop Manager and Trainer

Special Group of Interest in Programming Contests (SGIPC), KUET, Bangladesh

2012-2015